I remember when Taiwan started the so-called Democratization process
Many American politicians said that Taiwan’s democracy
would be a beacon for mainland China.
Compared to what they keep claiming,
the thing they do not tell you is
the so-called Taiwan style democracy can be manipulated.
What is the difference between the Taiwan separatists and the Hong Kong separatists?
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 微信公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Hello everyone! Welcome to China Now!
We are here to position China, and understand China!
We know that the Taiwan area of China will hold
a local leader election in 2020.
We closely follow the political ecology, people's livelihood, and public opinion on Taiwan Island.
Today we invited Professor Zhang Weiwei, Director of the China Institute of Fudan University.
And Ms. Huang Zhixian, a well-known political commentator from Taiwan.
We will discuss this topic together.
Now, I'll give the stage to Professor Zhang for an opening remark.
I am very glad to have Ms. Huang here in our program.
So as we all know that Ms. Huang is a well-known media personality in Taiwan
She supports the unification of our country,
and the ‘one country two systems’ principle.
On Oct 1st, She was at Tiananmen Square
to attend the National Day ceremony.
I saw an interview of her.
She said she was so excited and touched.
"Taiwan will return for unification."
She really moved us.
We also admire your courage.
Especially in the current political ecology of Taiwan,
your voice is very precious and
important in such an environment.
So again, we are very happy to have you here and have a discussion about Taiwan's democracy.
Thank you, Prof. Zhang, and thanks to the host.
It is an honor to come to China Now.
Every time, I say I am Taiwanese, so of course, I am Chinese.
But if you say such a thing in Taiwan, you will be treated as insane.
Then every day you feel the pressure
as if you are living a life as a spy.
The question is, why are you not allowed
to live an ordinary human life
in a place claiming to be free and to have human rights?
This is what I want to discuss today.
From the perspective a Chinese national, I will review what Taiwan has gone through,
And how did Taiwan become what it is today,
and what should Taiwan do in the future?
Right.
So today, we will have an in-depth interpretation of Taiwan.
Firstly, Prof. Zhang will give a speech,
then Ms. Huang will also give a speech,
In the end, we will open the floor for questions and discussion.
Now, I will give the stage to Professor Zhang.
I gave a speech at Southeast Television in 2016.
I gave an example at the end of that speech.
I compared the rapid development of infrastructure in the Mainland and the situation in Taiwan.
The measure is the performance gap caused by the different political systems across the strait.
I said,
It was 1996 when I first visit Taiwan.
They decided to build a subway,
known as Mass Rapid Transit (MRT) in Taiwan.
The full length is 51 km from Central Taipei to Taoyuan International Airport.
But 20 years passed, and it was still not completed.
During this period, they had 13 Ministers of Transportation.
Most of them were appointed for political reasons, but not for doing real business.
But what happened in Mainland China in those 20 years?
Mainland China built the largest national highway network,
and also the largest and best high-speed train network
All the cities that meet the conditions have built subways.
Shanghai has built the world's longest metro mileage from zero.
So this is what I said:
With such an obvious gap between the performance of two political systems,
some of us still believed that the Taiwan system represented the future of China.
I said, "They must've had some brain damage"
“or their heads are filled with water.”
At least they were unable to see the truth from simple facts.
I was targeting the "leading" public intellectuals
when I said this.
I didn't expect my words to spread to Taiwan like
"tossing a stone that creates thousands of waves".
On December 7th that year, Taiwan's
China Times published an editorial.
The title is ’Is There Any Institutional Advantage in Taiwan Democracy?‘
The editorial quoted what I said.
It says some mainland intellectuals believes that
the past 20 years of democratization in Taiwan not only failed to be a good reference for the mainland,
but also a lesson taught with a negative example.
The article also says: It is not the first time for Zhang Weiwei to comment on Taiwan like this.
Two years ago, in 2014,
When the Taiwan Sunflower Student Movement ended,
he gave a speech on the Taiwan Democracy's problems on Phoenix Television
with the title: From Hope to Disappointment.
The author may not know that
I mentioned this several times on many occasions:
Without help from mainland China
Taiwan democracy will fall from hope to not only disappointment but also desperation.
Mainland China's model enables the mainland's economy to take off.
It also brings numerous developmental opportunities for Taiwan.
Then the mainland is willing to share these opportunities with our compatriots in Taiwan.
This interesting editorial goes on to says:
Based on the high rating of this show [on Phonix TV],
a large number of elites in mainland China has gradually turned their impression of Taiwan from
"people are the most beautiful scenery in Taiwan"
to "a demonstration of falling behind the mainland".
In other words, the Democratic achievements
that Taiwanese were proud of
is not attractive to the people over the past 20 years of cross-strait interactions.
Instead, they are avoiding it out of fear.
And many of those who hold this view are intellectuals.
We should also ask ourselves, is Taiwan’s example of democracy really worthy of pride?
It is true that Taiwan has experienced political party alternations for three times
However, time and again, it creates more serious social cleavages each time.
I am afraid that after this year's party alternation,
Taiwanese won't even have a chance to feel good about themselves.
In the end, the author of this editorial sighed:
When people with different positions keep on arguing in the media or on the streets every day,
when Taiwan's society is filled with anxiety,
we don’t need to wait for mainland scholars, like Zhang Weiwei, to make negative comments.
Taiwan’s mainstream public opinion has already rated Taiwan’s democracy through polls, hasn't it?
When it gets popular to treat Taiwan as a negative example,
none of us feels good.
But should we also reflect on ourselves rationally?
How can we say we have a more advanced system without rational re-thinking?
Interestingly, when guancha.cn firstly shared this editorial,
netizens had an enthusiastic discussion.
A Chinese expat living in Boston in the US
wrote an interesting comment:
When Taiwan Taoyuan MRT was planned in 1996,
they said that the trial operation would start soon.
No matter what, its construction completed in twenty years.
The cost is approximately 26 billion RMB, for 51 kilometers.
That is amazing!
Look at Boston, the city where I live,
there is a central tunnel project,
AKA the Big Dig.
It's just 12 something kilometers.
But 45 years passed
and the construction has not finished yet.
Planned in 1971, began in 1991 and is still in progress...
15 billion US dollars have been spent, which is 100 billion RMB.
Almost 4 times higher than Taoyuan MRT
We see that big trouble brought by the western model
is the endless disputes triggered by all kinds of interest groups and politicians.
As a result,
the overall interests of the people including infrastructure are sacrificed.
For example, California wants to build a high-speed rail, since the 1980s.
So far, zero kilometer has been built.
Because all the senators demanded a stop to be built in their county,
otherwise, the high-speed rail was not allowed to pass.
Building high-speed rail will harm the interests of airlines
the interests of car companies
and the interests of hotels and other industries.
These companies had strong lobbying groups
and were able to start various lawsuits.
Overall, the western model does have a big problem.
Without reform,
whether it is the United States or Taiwan area,
I am afraid that they will only decline all the way.
I remember, when Taiwan first started the so-called Democratization process,
many American politicians said that Taiwan’s democracy would be a beacon for mainland China.
Now even the American Democracy Beacon is swaying.
Our netizens joke that the US is "the Beacon Country".
The US has already lost its own direction,
not to mention Taiwan's beacon.
Can it even illuminate the way for itself?
So what went wrong in Taiwan's Democracy?
Let me discuss with you a little bit.
First of all,
let's look at the outcomes of Taiwan's democratization in the past 30 years
The first is a serious economic downturn.
Taiwan’s economy has gone from the top of "The Four Asian Tigers" to the bottom.
Lee Teng-hui, elected in 1996, implemented the economic policy of “patience without haste”
As a result, Taiwan lost its opportunity to develop in the mainland market.
Chen Shui-bian, elected in 2000, changed seven Premiers in eight years.
He focused on balancing powers instead of developing the economy.
For eight consecutive years, the public investment was negative, and economic declined rapidly.
Ma Ying-jeou, elected in 2008, had even lower approval ratings than Chen Shui-bian's.
But he did one thing right:
acknowledging the 1992 Consensus.
It stabilized cross-strait relations for a period of time,
and strengthened economic integration with the mainland.
Compared to the Mainland, Taiwan’s economy changed like the Yellow River’s course.
When Taiwan’s so-called democratization started
in the late 1980s,
Taiwan’s economy was about 45% of the mainland’s.
30 years have passed,
Taiwan's economy today
is only about 4% of the mainland economy.
The revenue of Shenzhen city now
surpasses the total fiscal revenue of Taiwan.
In other words,
The budgets made by the mayor of Shenzhen are larger than Taiwan governor's.
The real income of most people,
including college graduates
has not increased for the past 20 years.
Chip engineers in Taiwan
have moved to the mainland for work.
Because the mainland’s income is three times that of Taiwan’s
The second is intensifying political strife.
Some people still believe that Taiwan’s democracy has at least enabled party alternation for several times
They see this as a great achievement.
Actually after each alternation,
the ruling party begins to plunder,
liquidate and retaliate another party.
For example, after Tsai Ing-wen came to power,
she didn't prioritize economic issues and people’s livelihood.
Instead, she was keen on promoting so-called transformational justice.
The Democratic Progressive Party (DPP) in Taiwan used its majority vote advantage
and passed regulations on the disposition of ill-gotten party assets.
That is to deprive Kuomintang (KMT,
aka the Nationalist Party) of its property
so that Kuomintang will not have enough resources for elections.
DPP also passed the transitional justice act.
The intention is to portray the DPP as the incarnation of democracy,
and make the KMT the incarnation of autocracy,
to continue the political strife between the two sides.
Then under those maneuvers by the DPP’s,
seeking independence is democracy
and developing relations with the mainland is autocracy.
This situation can also be seen in the chaos in Hong Kong today:
Anti-Mainland is democracy;
Pro-Mainland is autocracy.
I call this the extreme of ignorance.
We’ve seen a lot of physical assaults in Taiwan’s Legislative Yuan on TV.
There is a statistic,
from 2008 to 2016,
8 years，
the DPP occupied the rostrum nearly a hundred times when the legislature was in session.
There were various physical conflicts, including deliberate attacks.
How can such a democracy win the respect of others?
Taiwan’s media ecology has also undergone tremendous changes.
Taiwanese media in the two-Chiangs period [1949-1987]
was called pet dogs.
Now they are called mad dogs.
Ethnic conflicts were deliberately provoked"
the outsider vs the local;
tearing apart Taiwanese and Chinese groups.
The government lost its ability to integrate society.
The third is increased corruption.
After the democratization of Taiwan, the underworld and money intervene in politics as they please.
Democratization quickly turned into marketization.
Chen Shui-bian acquired a shocking amount of properties during his 8 years in office.
He went to jail
and got released on bail.
I don't want to keep on talking about this -
we're all familiar with this story.
Back in 2009,
before the mainland issued "The Eight Regulations",
Political and Economic Risk Consultancy (PERC) published a report.
The report believed the level of corruption in Taiwan is higher than in mainland China
That made Ma Ying-jeou heartbroken.
In the Ma Ying-jeou period, Ma Ying-jeou himself was relatively incorruptible.
But there were many corruption cases -
he couldn't control his subordinates.
So his administration didn't have a good reputation among the people.
Corruptions of senior KMT officials are reported one after another.
Taiwanese people sighed that both blue (KMT) and green (DPP) are greedy.
Various forms of bribery, including election bribery, remain unabated.
The latest scandal is:
On Tsai Ing-wen’s official airplane, there were officials smuggling nearly 10,000 cigarettes.
The fourth is that Taiwan’s cultural soft power over the mainland has declined on all fronts.
The mainland TV series Empresses in the Palace was popular in Taiwan when I visited Taiwan in 2013.
Actually, Mainland’s historical dramas were aired in Taiwan as big hits:
The Empress of China [Wu Zetian],
Kangxi Dynasty,
Yongzheng Dynasty,
The Emperor Han Wu,
The Grand Mansion Gate,
Qiao's Grand Courtyard etc..
Their ratings are quite good in Taiwan.
Then DPP politicians believe that the mainland is brainwashing the Taiwanese.
They worry a bit too much.
Twenty or thirty years ago,
the entire mainland was listening to Teresa Teng and watching Chiung Yao's drama.
It feels like "you're on the other side of Yellow River after 30 years" [its course changes frequently].
Mainland e-commerce is also changing the way of life of many in Taiwan.
Taobao has a lot of fans.
As I mentioned earlier,
according to my research on Taiwan's democracy,
I have always been pessimistic on it -
from hope to disappointment.
And without help from mainland China, it would fall from hope to desperation.
I hold this opinion for all the non-Western societies which adopt the Western political model.
If unfortunately, the Hong Kong Color Revolution succeeds,
then Hong Kong will directly fall from hope to desperation.
This is another big topic for us to talk about in the future.
What I’m talking about today is what's next for Taiwan’s democracy.
I guess it's an even greater disappointment,
but may not be desperation for a while.
Why not?
For a few reasons:
The first is that before the democratization,
in the two-Chiangs period,
especially during the Chiang Ching-kuo period [autocracy 1978-1988],
Taiwan was initially modernized.
The middle class had a relatively large proportion in the society.
If the Western democratic model was adopted from the beginning,
I believe it would be impossible for Taiwan to achieve initial modernization
The second is Chinese traditional culture.
It was uninterrupted and inherited in Taiwan.
It means
as long as Taiwan can maintain basic stability,
people work hard,
focus on education and work,
then its economy will not collapse
Thirdly, very importantly,
It is the impact of the China model.
In a sense, the China model saved Taiwan.
Economically, the China model has brought about the rapid rise of mainland China.
It provides a lot of opportunities for Taiwan’s economy and people.
Politically, the China model selects leaders through a meritocratic system.
More rational and mature compared to the leaders elected by populism in Taiwan.
For example in 2008,
the West provoked riots in Tibet.
At that time, Ma Ying-jeou, under pressure from the DPP, also claimed to boycott the Beijing Olympics.
However, the mainland leaders weighed the pros and cons,
and didn't take action on that.
Instead, they focused on the long-term interests of the people on both sides of the strait.
It avoided the deterioration of the cross-strait relationship.
If both of us were led by populism-elected leaders,
the cross-strait relations would expect a violent turmoil.
Why Taiwan’s democracy may bring greater disappointment?
Because of Taiwan's democratic predicament
is mainly caused by some deep-seated structural problems.
I will share some of my thoughts.
First of all, a relatively mature democratic system
focuses more on debating public policy issues,
rather than ideologies.
Well today, from Washington to London,
everyone is arguing fiercely about ideological issues.
As a consequence, the governance capacity of Western countries has dropped sharply.
And that is even more true in the Taiwan area.
A mature democratic system must be built based on a broad consensus
on the most fundamental political issues concerning the nation and the state.
And Taiwan can't do this.
When the mainstream of society is arguing about
"loving Taiwan or betraying Taiwan",
this society will fall into intense confrontations.
What is more, it’s easy for politicians to play the populist card
to get votes by inciting conflicts among ethnic groups.
The result is that the ethnic groups are torn apart and in constant fights.
The second is that Taiwan’s legal system does not have enough credibility.
For example, people were not satisfied with the court's ruling that
helped with Chen Shui-bian's re-election
based on the two bullets they found.
It was 2004.
They made this ruling.
So millions of "red shirts" went to the streets to protest.
This reflects the people’s suspicion of the existing judicial system
and how problems are solved within this system.
Taiwan’s judicial system and investigatory
system has not yet been able to establish a mechanism
that transcends partisanship and political differences.
The third point is the design of Taiwan's electoral system is problematic.
The first round is a simple majority system
and it determines the result.
Then in the 2000 elections, there was internal conflicts within the KMT.
As a result, Chen Shui-bian was elected with a little more than 30% of the vote.
In France, for example, if the candidates get less than 50% of the votes in round one,
a second round of voting will be held.
The result could have been completely different.
But it’s very difficult to amend election-related laws.
This is also the general problem brought by institutional and legal rigidity in the Western model.
For example, if the United States wants to reform, it must amend the constitution.
But this kind of constitutional amendment is almost impossible
with current opposition between American parties.
So there is no way to make a reform.
The fourth point is civic culture:
The civic culture is seriously inadequate.
The so-called civic culture is
what I call
specific customs and attitudes.
The feature is to respect your opponent and respect the minority.
In other words,
Taiwan merely achieved electoral democracy,
but civic culture is still gravely absent.
It’s full of what the academia calls "illiberal democracy."
In such an atmosphere,
‘Taiwanese’ and ‘love Taiwan’ have become populist symbols.
All claims of political opponents can be demonized
and discredited through political labeling
and other means.
They can bring out the dark side in human nature.
In the spring of 2014,
Taiwan's college students occupied the Legislative Yuan and hit the Executive Yuan
in their Sun Flower movement despising the legal system.
They protested against the cross-strait service trade agreement which benefits Taiwan overall.
And behind this chaos
is the political strife
the loss of rational judgment,
and the sinking of the entire society.
I think, the fifth point is,
the excessive influence of the US and the US model.
In Taiwan, America's influence has reached everywhere.
This affects Taiwan’s own political exploration.
The American model itself is facing huge challenges:
capital is harvesting political and social powers.
And the gamification of democracy -
democracy became a game.
"When the top beam is crooked, the entire house is twisted."
America's model has fallen into a "Trump dilemma".
Or we can also call it the TRuly Unreliable Man Problem (TRUMP) dilemma.
Do you think there is still a future for Taiwan to follow the US model?
From the lessons of Taiwan’s democratic development,
I believe it leads to a few thoughts.
Firstly, we must break through the Western narrative.
They say there are only two types of systems in the world: democracy and autocracy.
This narrative does not hold.
If we must use a dichotomy to look at the systems in the world,
then I would say the difference is only between good governance and bad governance.
This analysis framework is more fact-based.
I believe it will eventually become the mainstream of the world.
Secondly, Chinese traditional culture and historical education
were not interrupted in Taiwan during the two Chiangs period.
But now it is increasingly disrupted under
the manipulation of Taiwan separatists.
Taiwan's civil society inherited good qualities
"gentle, kind, respectful, thrifty, and tolerant."
But now it is getting more and more divided.
It's a pity.
What would happen if Taiwan had not copied the American democratic model,
but had developed in accordance with the logic of Chinese traditional culture?
In the meantime, if it also absorbed some reasonable elements from Western system,
perhaps Taiwan could have developed a higher-quality consultative democracy
rather than a confrontational American democracy.
A livelihood-oriented democracy, rather than an American democracy that politicizes all issues.
I think Taiwan has paid a heavy price for its unwise choices and will continue to do so.
Thirdly, using the Taiwan area as a reference,
we can see our own path and model has a bright future.
Thirty years ago, Taiwan felt so good about itself.
When the mainland economy just began to take off,
Taiwan had already taken a step ahead.
but today, the strength of mainland of Taiwan has undergone enormous changes:
The mainland has risen rapidly and Taiwan quickly declined.
A feature of China's model is that it can formulate and implement policies and plans
that are in line with long-term interests.
The stable formulation and implementation of a series of five-year plans
laid the foundation for China's rise.
However, after Taiwan’s “democratization”,
it lost the mid-term to long-term capability to design and execute plans.
Also, in terms of politics, the Western model highlights 'one person, one vote'
while the Chinese model emphasizes meritocracy.
The two methods can compete.
In the era of new media,
Western democratic models are becoming more populist and gamified.
It's increasingly difficult to produce good leaders.
The trend of changing powers across the strait is irreversible.
I remember that when I talked about the Hong Kong issue last time, I said:
If Hong Kong's capitalist system refuses to reform,
Hong Kong may sink and cause significant harm to the interests of Hong Kong people.
We're very reluctant to see this.
Still, I do not exclude the possibility that
Hong Kong will eventually become an education base to raise confidence in the mainland model and system.
This successful city, which refuses reforms and lost its ability to reform, will sink all the way.
Just like Taiwan - it has already become such an education base.
I hope Hong Kong will not become another.
In short, Taiwan urgently needs political reform today.
Otherwise, it will continue to decline.
We hope that Taiwan can promote substantive political reforms,
that the people on both sides of the strait will keep going closer,
that the two sides of the strait can achieve common prosperity,
and that our county can eventually be unified.
I also believe that this is an irreversible historical trend.
Okay, that's all for my speech today.
Thank you.
Thank you, Professor Zhang, for the keynote.
It gives a deep analysis of the Taiwan issue.
Next, let’s welcome Ms. Huang Zhixian.
You come from Taiwan,
What is Taiwan like in your eyes?
Please.
Thank you.
When I was in Xiamen in June [2019],
I said that
our generation would bring Taiwan home.
Why was I so confident?
Because I know what I see now
is waht I will see in the future.
When my generation grew up, all Taiwanese identified Chinese.
99.9999%.
When we were growing up, we were always thinking
how we can rejuvenate China,
how we can make China the greatest country,
and how can we "rescue" our mainland compatriots who were "suffering"?
Every day, we thought about whether we need revolutions or reforms.
This is how the intellectuals of our generation are.
Because at that time, our textbooks told us since we were very young
that we are Chinese -
all the dynasties back to the ancient Peking Man.
Although we hated to memorize the facts,
textbooks are like the software on a computer:
once installed, it will follow the instructions of the program.
Think about this:
when Lee Teng-hui used his power as the KMT president and the leader of Taiwan in early 1990s
to make the first "Taiwan independence" textbook.
At that time, he invited DPP members
to open champagnes in his office.
He said that "In 20 years after we publish this textbook,"
"all the Taiwanese people will always be our people even if we do nothing at all."
It is simple math:
people who began their junior high school in early 1990s
are now in their thirties.
Therefore, a recent poll in Taiwan shows that 85 % of people under 30
consider themselves Taiwanese, not Chinese.
College graduates in Taiwan no longer
know who Zhuge Liang is
because they don't have it in their textbooks.
They are saying democracy in Taiwan all the time,
but isn't democracy "having the people making the decisions".
No, they do not tell you that democracy can be manipulated.
Why so many Western scholars start
thinking about the end of democracy?
Because after the implementation of
'one-person, one-vote' suffrage,
the rich people can finally buy votes with money,
because in Taiwan and the United States,
and most places in Europe,
most of the media are controlled by capital.
I can buy newspapers.
And then I can also buy two TV channels,
a radio channel,
and online platforms.
I can buy as many as possible,
and then I can decide what to promote.
I can also affect the MPs
because they need to make appearances to be elected.
They need to communicate and advertise.
If the MPs are not obedient,
they will not be allowed to appear on TV.
If the MPs dare to help my opponents,
my newspaper will criticize them every day.
That was how they did it back then.
This is a dilemma in democratic system design -
especially obvious in Taiwan.
You have to look 5, 10, and 20 years ahead.
But after 5, 10, or 20 years,
this ruler is no longer in office.
When Taiwan was under Japanese colonial rule,
85% of the farmers in Taiwan were tenant farmers with no land.
After the "two Chiangs" came back,
almost all the third-class tenant farmers and poor households
had their rice to eat, and they all had their land.
Chen Shui-bian's family was one of them:
he was born in a tenant farmer family and
obtained some land thanks to the policy.
The "two Chiangs" began obligational education.
So that poor children could go to the military and public school.
Chen Shui-bian's sisters all passed exams to be teachers
and they had life-time employment.
It only took one generation to change a family's life.
Taiwan then began to develop textile and light industry, as well as electronics industries.
Every step was contrary to Western theories.
For example, the government found they need to build highways.
When the construction started, everyone opposed it.
"There are barely any cars on the streets."
"Highways are for the rich."
If this was in Taiwan's current system,
they would never be able to build any highway.
Taiwanese would still be pushing ox-wagons, I'm sure.
Because everyone is opposed to it.
Therefore, the inner dilemma of democracy is
that most people really have no time or ability
to understand a complicated plan or policy.
I was studying at Taipei First Girls High School, the best high school.
My father wanted me to study medicine.
However, my interest was always in Chinese.
My father told me "either medicine or quit".
So I dropped out of school.
Since then, I worked for seven years.
I worked as a house painter, served dishes,
drove a taxi,
and worked in all kinds of restaurants.
After I made enough money,
I went to university in the United States.
I was also working part-time,
and then went to the UK for a master's degree.
I was always working at the bottom of society.
I worked in Taiwan, the US, and the UK.
I know that when you are busy making a living,
you won't understand what politicians are talking about.
If I am still interested in politics
and I want to cast a vote,
what do I base my vote on?
This girl is so beautiful and you feel an affinity with her first sight.
Some Taiwanese cast "the pig brother votes".
Political parties send out beautiful young girls,
and they appeal to people to vote for her.
The "pig brothers" come,
vote for her and she will be elected.
In other words, if I want to impress you and make you remember me,
I have to make an unexpected move and get media coverage.
That's why people start fights - because the media will report.
Sometimes they fight during the day,
and drink together at night.
That's all true. But why?
Because we have common interests.
We fight as I represent the KMT and you represent the DPP.
There are some pro-independence members of DPP,
so they have to show that they're working hard for "Taiwan independence."
And as a member of KMT, I need to criticize DPP.
Okay, once the reporters have set up the cameras,
our fight starts.
After the show,
we still have some bills to review.
My funder might be the same as yours.
You may not know this, but there are so many ridiculous things in Taiwan.
The KMT and DPP share the same funder.
For example, I am a rich entrepreneur.
I pay the KMT 3 million
and DPP 5 million
and People First Party 1 million
and some amount for some party - I buy them all!
So when I want to pass a bill, you better all behave.
Don't really review it.
You can make some noise but the bill
must pass in no more than 3 days.
This is a true story that happens in Taiwan,
and it also occurs in the United States.
The democracy that Taiwan flaunts is a trap.
One significant difference from the US is that the US doesn't have a national identity problem.
But this is a problem in Taiwan.
The ruling party intentionally makes this an issue.
They want to sneakily complete "Taiwan independence",
under the cover of the KMT heritage
and the 600,000 treasures in the Waishuangxi Palace Museum.
The first generation who followed the KMT from the mainland to Taiwan
is withering one after another.
Seventy years have passed,
and many of them are no longer alive.
This is the reason for my great fear.
In the end,
Let me talk about this book I published in 2004.
It was about how Chen Shui-bian used two bullets to manipulate and falsify.
"Trambling Future: Taiwan's New Dictatorship"
At that time, I compared the DPP with the Nazis.
I found they had a strikingly similar routine:
to manipulate hatred.
How?
Nazi Hitler turned Germany into dictatorship
under its most democratic state of the Weimar Republic.
He utilized a seemingly democratic system,
and finally turned it into Nazi, into a fascist state.
Even though this has happened long ago,
it can still happen in Taiwan.
It is very simple to manipulate.
The two sides across the strait will eventually reunify,
we must reunify,
we will definitely reunify,
and I believe I can see it in my life.
I think,
the Chinese people must be confident and assertive.
China has its own territory, its own land,
and its own people -
we must walk our own path.
Just imagine, if the mainland uses Taiwan's method,
then who will help the poor areas?
For example, Shanghainese will just need to think about their own interests.
Why should they help others?
And no one will help resolve the rich and poor divide.
Therefore, this so-called democratic system devastates human rights most.
Thank you.
Thank you both for the keynotes.
Professor Zhang gave us a few insights about Taiwan.
One of them is to break away from the Western paradigm.
Step out of it.
Ms Huang also mentioned that Taiwan’s current problem is
the so-called Western model predicament.
Can Taiwanese break through such a predicament?
I am relatively pessimistic.
Because once entering this Western model,
as I always said, it would either go from hope to disappointment or hope to despair.
It is hard to jump out.
Taiwan may be one of the few places where there is still an opportunity,
and the opportunity is peaceful reunification.
After reunification, even if it is "one country, two systems",
the policy will also advance with the times.
As I suggested, Taiwan's democratic system
should focus more on people's livelihood
and be livelihood-oriented.
It should also embrace more of China's traditional "consensus-seeking thinking"
instead of confrontation in democracy.
The mainland can provide a lot of experience.
I think Taiwan has a lot to learn.
This system must be changed.
I am only slightly more optimistic than Ms. Huang on one thing:
I still believe that "the trend is stronger than individuals".
I can understand that under the current "Taiwan independence" climate,
young people in Taiwan have been experiencing increasing depression.
Still, I believe that "there is a reverse after the peak."
The mainland also needs to progressively put measures in place.
I believe we will find a solution.
This is the reason why we feel as if we were
"working as spies in our enemies"
but we think we must do it.
Many audiences told me that
it's been 20 years that they fear to speak out
that they identify as Chinese in public.
Can you imagine how absurd that is?
Our system is one China -
Taiwan is China's territory.
It is enforced in Taiwan's legal system.
However, they just dare not publicly say that they are Chinese.
We are scared of reforms in Taiwan.
Every time they come up with a reason, saying "the people hate this"
and "I'm doing this for the people".
Then they did a lot of tricks under the counter
so that it will benefit themselves more.
But people will suffer even more.
But The people have already voted,
so they have to wait for the next four years before they can change anything.
Then they would do the same manipulation four years later -
getting more good-looking men and women to dance on the stage,
and then re-election is secured.
This dilemma of democracy will not find a solution.
Taiwan has this democracy dilemma and
the predicament in its [social] structure.
I feel that the faster the reunification,
the faster this problem can be solved.
It is challenging for Taiwan to solve the problem by itself.
A person cannot pull themselves off the ground by pulling their hair.
If you follow Taiwan's news,
you will find that the PMs have physical conflicts a lot.
As you mentioned,
they often put on a show of "gang fights" with total disregard of any manners.
It makes everyone astonished.
It is a manifestation of Taiwan's political ecology.
A few days ago, I also saw news saying that
the PMs used "screaming rubber chickens" when they fought.
It is a toy that makes a screaming sound when you press it.
As a result, the hall was filled with noisy screams.
It was truly disgraceful.
However, it is such people who are, in their own words, "serving the people".
But the people do not see any social development happening.
So next, let's open up the discussion.
What are your opinions on the Taiwan issue?
What are your thoughts?
I am a graduate student at Shanghai University.
I got many classmates from Taiwan.
They said that if there was a war in the future,
they would still serve as soldiers in Taiwan.
And their bullets would shot toward us.
Wow, you have already discussed such details!
It was in junior high school,
and he is serving in the military now.
Not voluntarily.
If he does not go back,
he will become a deserter and sent to jail.
This is a local regulation in Taiwan.
My question today is that
the Hong Kong issue has been on our nerves recently.
Compared with "Taiwan separatists",
have the recent actions of the "Hong Kong separatists" caused a more negative impact internationally?
What are the similarities and differences between these two forces?
Their similarity is simple:
they will perish.
For differences,
"Hong Kong separatism" is a relatively new thing.
If I remember correctly,
the Hong Kong Federation of Students started a magazine a few years ago.
Their articles started to explore the possibility of "Hong Kong independence".
Their theories have an even weaker foundation.
As for "Taiwan independence",
it can be traced back to Japan's surrender in 1945.
Some Japanese were left on the island to promote "Taiwan independence."
In the "Two Chiangs" period,
Communist Party and Taiwan separatism were both suppressed.
I remember that I told you about Li Ao's story before.
He was in the KMT's prison.
He said the Taiwan separatists were a bunch of cowards.
Mostly prisoners were pro-Communist or Communists party members.
There was only one "Taiwan independence" guy who they found out later was mentally ill.
Hence Li Ao felt that they had no guts.
That's what Li Ao said.
It somehow reflects how Taiwan separatism was controlled
in the "Two Chiangs" period.
With the beginning of democratization,
"Taiwan separatists" helped the DPP become a formal party,
and they even stepped onto the political arena.
This is the process.
Fortunately, we have a very clear "Anti-Secession Law" for these separatists，
which was passed in 2005.
It states several conditions
under which we can resort to non-peaceful measures.
Regarding "Hong Kong separatism", if you have read
about the communique of the Fourth Plenary Session of the 19th Central Committee.
It says: "Establish and improve the legal system and enforcement mechanism of Hong Kong SAR
to safeguard national security."
This voices our position out loud.
Let's wait and see how it implements.
In the end, I hold the same opinion:
no matter how rampant they are at the moment, the trend does not stand with them.
The rise of China is unstoppable.
Also, I believe that in our new era,
we can solve all these problems.
In my opinion, what they have in common is:
first, as Prof. Zhang said,
they will definitely perish.
They won't succeed,
and China will eventually be unified.
Secondly is that Hong Kong and Taiwan were once colonies,
so there is plenty of room
for foreign forces to intervene.
Taiwan has a lot of influence left by Japan.
Now Taiwan is very close to Japan in economics and trade.
Japan often unites with Taiwanese companies to enter the mainland market.
They know that Japanese companies cannot win the mainland market directly.
So they share common interests.
Therefore, when I used to talk about Japan's colonial exploitation on my shows,
Japanese trading associations and Japanese companies would call and protest.
This manifests their influence.
When the Sunflower Student Movement happened,
the Japanese trading associations sent supplies
to the "Legislative Yuan" the next morning.
It was so fast.
So America and Japan are the main forces
that were operating in Taiwan.
Same with Hong Kong.
Hong Kong separatists learnt from Taiwan
and started the 2014 "Umbrella Movement".
The leaders are the same as this year's [protests].
They went to Taiwan for training after the "3-19 shooting incident ".
So we can say that Hong Kong separatists and Taiwan separatists are from the same stream.
Okay, let’s welcome the next question.
Please also briefly introduce yourself.
Hi everyone, I am a police student from Hunan.
I think that every Chinese national should care about the Taiwan issue.
What I would like to know is,
many young Taiwanese have come to the mainland,
have seen the mainland's convenient transportation,
mobile payment,
and the job opportunities in the mainland's huge market.
What kind of influence will they bring back to Taiwan?
Thank you.
Please sit down. Another good question.
And I noticed that he views the Taiwan issue as a duty for all Chinese people.
Thanks for your question.
I also have many Taiwanese friends
living on the island or in Shanghai.
They were shocked
when they first came to the mainland.
A high proportion of Taiwanese feel the same.
But there is an important reason why we can't overestimate [the influence].
As Ms Huang mentioned, the closed [political] eco-system in Taiwan.
It claims to have media freedom and to be a democratic society.
The reality is the right opposite: undemocratic and lacking freedom.
It is the same for Hong Kong.
HK is so close to Shenzhen,
but most people don't know the [economic] miracle of Shenzhen.
Even the US is afraid, but HK is unaware.
The local media is controlled by capital
which does not want you to know the real situation.
So those returning young Taiwanese will have some impacts but to a limited extent.
On the other hand, when we discuss in the mainland
our work related to Taiwan,
when we discuss political issues, systems, democracy, freedom of speech, etc.
people may feel that their teachers are not convincing.
This is a common problem:
many of us are not confident.
LIke I mentioned,
some public intellectuals still believe that Taiwan's system is the future
and this will have considerable impacts on academia.
Therefore, we must have confidence from our hearts
so that we can do well when it comes to Taiwan and Hong Kong affairs.
But also I believe such influence will gradually expand.
In the end, we will find out that's the truth.
It will form a general trend,
and the trend will be unstoppable.
Let me share a news story a couple days ago.
A man who made a call to
a live broadcast of a Taiwanese radio program.
He said he lived in Yilan, Taiwan and later moved to Xiamen, Fujian.
And…Oh, some of us here have heard this too.
Mr Li, where do you live?
I'm in Xiamen.
I moved to Xiamen from Yilan.
My father joined the DPP with Chen Ding-nan.
He is now so mad.
He didn't want to come to Xiamen before,
but I brought him here last year.
Since then, every time he watches Formosa TV (FTV) and Sanlih E-Television (SET)
he gets furious!
He forbids my son, mother, and uncle to watch them.
No SET and no FTV!
The two channels mislead our children
and spread fake news!
These media really ruin Taiwan!
Mr. Li,
don't be so excited,
Will you come back next year to vote?
I don't just go back to vote.
There are more than 70 people in my family.
No matter who they are, they are not allowed to vote for the DPP!
I will break up with them if anyone votes for the DPP.
The more they pro DPP they were,
the less they want to vote for the DPP
once they come to the mainland,
and the more they want to reunify, do you understand?
So we've noticed this in the news.
About this question, I want to ask Ms Huang,
as we hope to learn more about each other through communication.
Especially for our friends in Taiwan to open their eyes to see the mainland, their homeland.
From your perspective,
how would they react [to mainland's growth]?
I should say
100% of them would be shocked.
The mainland is the "infrastructure monster".
But it can take more than ten years to build a road in Taiwan.
Not only high-speed rail or subway,
even a road can take a long time.
Why?
Because of various conflicts of interest.
The road has to pass by my house,
so my land will appreciate in value.
But not through my crop fields.
It must bypass my home.
Okay, I want this,
and you want that.
Let's compete.
I'll go see this PM and you ask that PM.
A few rounds later, when the mayor's term is over,
we start all over again.
So it can take forever.
Every Taiwanese coming to the mainland will be impressed.
Firstly, the development of the mainland is shockingly different from
DPP's propaganda media coverage, 99% of which is negative.
Why so different?
Secondly, the cultural shock.
I have told this joke many times.
It is a real story.
A "Taiwan separatist" came to Xiamen,
and messaged his friends on Line -
Taiwan uses Line instead of WeChat.
He said Xiamen also speaks Taiwanese!
When he returned to Taiwan,
of course, he knew that we are all Chinese.
But here comes the problem.
In the election last year,
a DPP PM had a scandal when a recording was leaked.
As a DPP member, he supports "Taiwan independence".
In the recording, he told his girlfriend,
"You don't know, I must rely on my DPP membership wo win this election."
"Once I'm elected, I can 'walk with winds' on the mainland."
You understand?
Many DPP people often come to the mainland.
Clearly, they know what's going on here,
but they have cultivated a group of "political customers".
The customers like to hear you cursing the mainland.
They only like "Taiwan independence" [ideas].
So the PM became a double-faced separatist.
For example, a DPP city councilor surnamed Tong,
He sings "We are brothers" whenever he comes to the mainland,
"We are good brothers."
Once he returns to Taiwan,
his curses on the mainland continue.
This is where we are.
So, in the end, does that work?
About 2/3 Taiwanese people
haven’t been to the mainland.
The more Taiwanese visit, the better.
Many pro-mainland young Taiwanese would stay here to study, work, and start a family.
When the election is coming,
going home just for the election can be expensive for them.
So they choose not to return and vote.
These people understand and identify with the mainland
and are against separatism. They all stay here.
The separatists are happy to see this.
"Go to your motherland, don’t vote here!"
As a result, the population in Taiwan becomes greener [more pro-DPP] and more pro-independence.
This issue is hard to address.
I want to take the opportunity to ask Ms. Huang a question,
which relates to the situation introduced by Professor Zhang.
For example,
a few years ago we saw some mainland movies and TV dramas gained popularity in Taiwan.
At that time, we thought it might be
our culture products were able to influence our compatriots across the strait.
Now it is more often, as you said,
they will identify themselves as Taiwanese rather than Chinese.
Our cultural products are seen as coming from another country,
just like the ones from Japan or the US.
Considered as imported cultural products.
Isn't it dangerous by this mean?
Can our cultural influence continue?
The cultural influence is definitely growing.
Taiwanese girls shop on Taobao.
Taiwanese women, I can say that they may have watched
"Empresses in the Palace"
for 30 times, 40 times, 50 times.
The series has been rebroadcast 100 times on TV.
This is the most popular drama
with Taiwanese girls.
Guys might be fond of mainland dramas such as "Three Kingdoms".
However, I must say that
it is still different from having a national identity.
Once it comes to national identity,
Most Taiwanese over 40, identify themselves as Chinese.
For the 50s, 70% to 80% may think they are Chinese.
Can't do anything about it.
How do you shape a person's national identity?
Their textbook is the answer, and the power of the government.
The DPP authorities "diligently" - in quotation marks -
trying to "de-Sinicize".
They did a lot in addition to modifying textbooks.
The most important one is The Forbidden City, as you mentioned earlier.
A Japanese journalist named Nojima Tsuyosh,
who later became a writer.
He wrote a story about The Forbidden City,
called "The Separation of the Two Old Palace".
He traced the stories of Taipei's Palace Museum.
DPP is working hard to open a Chiayi South museum in addition to the Tapei museum.
But why?
Because they want to remove the objects representing the Chinese civilization
which are displayed in the Taipei museum.
They want to exhibit the relics of native Taiwan
together with the relics from Southeast Asia and Japan
in the new Chiayi museum.
They are trying to make everyone feel that Taiwanese is part of Asia
by cutting off its ties with the Chinese civilization.
So everyone noticed their "efforts"
- again, in quotation marks -
is not only in textbooks but also in culture and many other aspects.
We need to be vigilant about this.
But as Ms. Huang said, they have already been doing these in Taiwan.
That's why we feel concerned.
Let's see if we have any more questions from the audience. All are Welcomed.
Yes, please.
You talked about the issue of voting.
My question is ...
We can often see a very contradictory phenomenon.
When any leader of Taiwan was in office,
various polls showed that their approval ratings were low.
But whenever there was an election or a change of term,
they could find their ways to get themselves re-elected.
My question is: What is the underlying reason for this result?
Does this result truly reflect the public opinion in Taiwan?
Please sit down. Also a good question.
The difference between polls and results …
Taiwan's polls can have all kinds of results.
A coupled days ago, on the press conference of the Taiwan Affairs Office of the State Council.
Some Taiwan reporter(s) said some polls showed that Taiwanese people do not support reunification.
The spokesperson replied,
we are aware of Taiwan media's ability to produce opinion polls.
You can produce any results you want.
They are not very credible.
Besides, Taiwan electoral politics now faces an issue.
Many other places also have such problems.
It is called the median voter.
Previously, blue or green were the majority,
but now it is the median voter.
I saw the latest analysis,
using Taipei as an example.
Taipei used to mainly be blue - supporting KMT.
Now it is 30% Blue, 20%Green -
so the other 50% is the median voters.
In the end, election results often depend on
the median voters.
It requires studying the population structure
and voting preferences of the median voters.
I think this is also a huge dilemma for "democratic systems".
According to our preliminary research,
the structure of median voters:
they are mainly young people and not particularly interested in politics.
In terms of preferences, incidents happening on the day of the election, or a week or three weeks before,
or a month before - often affect them significantly.
As you mentioned,
the 3-19 shooting changed Chen Shui-bian's election immediately.
The two bullets in 2004 -
I was watching TV at 1pm the day before voting.
All out of suddenly, bang!
then the News ticker started to roll...
That's even OK?
I said: Chen Shui-bian, well played!
Even the Americans felt the same.
Everybody knew he was playing [a trick],
but what could we do?
There was also a very dramatic twist in 2016.
What were they playing in 2016?
The night before voting,
my show was on broadcast until 10pm.
After 10 pm, no election-related activities were allowed.
I did not expect the videotape of Taiwanese actress Zhou Tzuyu to be broadcast intentionally
on Taiwan Internet and TV networks after 10 pm.
A lovely beautiful girl, all tearfully,
saying she was "bullied" by China's communist party.
On the taps, she said "I'm Chinese".
The Taiwanese otaku guys couldn't stand it.
The second day it was an "otaku walk-out" to vote.
Their votes were not for the DPP or the New Power Party.
Their votes were for Zhou Tzuyu.
They utilized Zhou Tzuyu to mobilize people.
She diverted a lot of votes.
Yes, an estimate of 1 million votes were diverted.
Many KMT "legislators" would have been elected,
but they lost the election in the end.
Theoretically,
a good political system should
consider people's overall interests,
at least the mid-to-long-term interests.
At least the interests for four years should be guaranteed.
However, one impulsive event can change the election result.
This person takes office for four years,
and there is no way to change the decision of your democracy.
This is a tragedy of the "democratic system" -
the tragedy of the Western model.
How can we solve this problem?
China Now with Zhang Weiwei
We all know that politics is a very serious and professional subject.
When we observe Taiwan,
we find that Taiwan's political environment,
as Ms. Huang told us, is more like a stage for shows.
It is also a kind of consumption and entertainment.
All in all, it has deviated from being professional.
This is also the biggest problem of "democratic politics" in the West.
Speaking of Taiwan, I have one more question for you to answer quickly.
We know that Taiwan has long been a vital pawn for the United States to constrain China.
It is also their essential part of the first island chain to block China's military forces.
Taiwan's political eco-system
is also inseparable from the US.
Can you also talk a bit about this?
The historical genes of the Taiwanese KMT
is to respect and fear the US.
The DPP need supports from the US
for "Taiwan independence".
They both hope the US to carry them
and have wasted a lot of resources and money from Taiwan people
to buy America's useless weapons.
But I think the US has too much to care about right now.
We all know that Trump withdrew troops from Syria.
Indeed, most American people do not want any more wars.
It's been decades of wars - it harasses the people and wastes money.
The infrastructure in the US is getting worse.
As a consequence, the US will give up Taiwan when the critical moment arrives.
This cannot be wrong because
Taiwan's position will gradually decline in America's overall strategic thinking
This is my basic judgment.
Therefore, whether the KMT or the DPP is elected,
they, more or less, want America to add more weight to their separatist plans.
Publicly or under the counter,
they will both completely fail in the end.
I think Hong Kong and Taiwan are
the two daggers held by the US to stab into China.
What is the magical use of Hong Kong and Taiwan?
That is, the US does not need to spend any money - they can even make some money.
It is using the Chinese to deal with the Chinese.
This hurts the most.
The US has passed several bills, one after another.
They all have violated the three communiqués on the establishment of China-US diplomatic relations.
Some US members of congress even said that
"It's time that we acknowledge Taiwan as a country."
They've already gone to far.
But he will not really support Taiwan's "independence."
What they want is to when the mainland cannot tolerate
and ideally when small-scale armed conflicts happen,
so the US can continue to sell weapons.
"Picking a chestnut from a fire."
[gaining little from taking a high risk]
Correct! In the end, the US sold weapons,
and it would tell Beijing that I can help to mediate.
They provoked the war,
and they also guided the mediation,
in between, they sold weapons.
America has asked Taiwan to be obedient
and forced American pork to enter Taiwan market.
"If you don't import my pork, I won't speak for you."
Okay, this is always their logic.
From the standpoint of the US,
it will always hold Taiwan’s on leash,
loose and tight, as it pleases.
Taiwan will be the piece of meat that America exclusively enjoys.
Ma Ying-jeou hoped to bring Taiwan closer to the mainland during his terms.
But when US threatened, Ma Ying-jeou immediately backed down.
The United States has thousands of ways to intimidate
leaders in Taiwan away from reunifying with the mainland.
We all know that some other countries like to play the Taiwan card.
One day, this card will be weaker and weaker.
We also know that President Xi said that the Taiwan issue was formed when our nation was weak and poor.
When we embrace the day of national revival,
that is the time of our cross-strait reunion.
Both of our guests have repeatedly said
that the two sides will eventually be reunified.
We look forward to that day.
Thank you both. And thanks to our audience today.
Thank you all. Goodbye.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 微信公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
[Preview of next episode]